Every day you make decisions and judgments.
Sometimes you're able to think about them
carefully, but other times you make them on
the fly using little information.
This is where heuristics come in.
Heuristics are straightforward rules of thumb
that we develop based on our past experiences.
They're cognitive tools that help us make quick decisions or judgments.
Life would be exhausting if we had to deliberate
over every one of the hundreds of choices
we make every day.
So instead we use our heuristics as shortcuts
to make judgements about the world around us.
For example, rather than spending time
deciding what to wear every day, you might
have some default outfits.
Or when faced with a lunch menu with too many
options, you may opt for what you've enjoyed
in the past.
Heuristics aren't about making the perfect
decision or judgment, just about making one
quickly.
Heuristics play a role in our reasoning about
the broader world too.
As an example, consider the rate of violence
in the world over the past century.
Is the world more or less violent in the past
20 years than previously?
Heuristic reasoning might lead to think that
the world is more violent today than it has
been in the past.
Every day we're confronted with images of
tragedy in the news and on social media.
We might reasonably assume that the world
is more violent today than ever before, using
what's called an "availability heuristic."
That is, examples of violence that so readily
available, we just naturally assume the world
is more violent today.
But in fact the world is more peaceful today
than ever before in human history.
We may hear a lot about violent events but
in terms of raw numbers, fewer people die
today at the hands of other humans beings
than ever before.
So that heuristic about how violent the world
is, is incorrect.
In fact, a slew of other heuristics can easily
to mistaken conclusions.
And it doesn't matter how smart or well educated
you are.
Anyone can place too much trust in the mental
shortcuts they use to make sense of the world.
Take this example.
Let's say a person tests positive for a rare
disease, one that only one-in-a-thousand people have.
What is the likelihood that he actually has
the disease?
Most of us would say the likelihood is very
high based on the test results alone.
But what if the results were inaccurate 10%
of the time?
If the false positive rate is 10%, a common
number in medical tests, then it is highly
unlikely our patient has the disease.
In fact, based on the prevalence of the disease
and the test result, we can be 99% sure he
doesn't have the disease.
This is because the odds of the getting a
false positive result, one in 10, are much
higher than the odds of actually having the
disease, one in 1,000.
But in multiple studies, physicians routinely
get this wrong, overestimating the likelihood
that their patient actually has the disease.
Psychologists call this the "representativeness
heuristic."
People assume an individual case is more representative than it actually is.
Our political views can especially suffer
from an over-reliance on heuristics.
Just consider how we deal with political issues.
We'll often let our political identities, and
our heuristics about how right we think they are,
stand in lieu of important details and
information we need to have an informed viewpoint.
Because our heuristics can so easily lead
us to faulty conclusions, it's important to
be humble about our views.
In light our fallibility, we have to do something
that doesn't come easy, we must recognize
that the world is an uncertain place and that
our judgements about it are often wrong.
We ought to listen to opinions we may initially
consider wrong or even offensive.
Our intuitions are useful, even necessary
when it comes to making
quick judgments about the world.
But that doesn't mean they're correct.
Recognizing the flawed nature of your thinking
is a bold first step to challenging it.